Finding Aid for Roy William Cowden papers, 1924-1960
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Roy William Cowden papers 1924-1960
Cowden, Roy William
1 linear foot
851017 Aa 2
Professor of English and first director of the Avery Hopwood Awards for writing at the University of Michigan. Correspondence, largely with students; manuscripts of writings; notes and class materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Roy W. Cowden (donor no. 3981 )
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Roy W. Cowden was born in 1883 at Fredonia, N.Y. He received a bachelor of arts degree from the University of Michigan in 1908 and a master's degree from Harvard University in 1909. He joined the U-M faculty in 1909 as an instructor in English, and was advanced to the rank of full professor in 1935. He was best known as director of the Avery and Jule Hopwood Awards Program in Creative Writing at the U-M, a post he held from 1934 until the time of his retirement in 1952. He died September 1961.
The collection consists of correspondence mainly with students and from the period of 1953 to 1955. In addition, there a series of his various writings, some teaching materials, and a speech.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Avery Hopwood and Jule Hopwood Prizes.; University of Michigan. Dept. of English Language and Literature.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Correspondence
  - Undated and fragmentary, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1924-1951 (Box 1)
  - 1952 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1953 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1953 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1954 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1954 (Box 1)
  - July-September 1954 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1954 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1955 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1955 (Box 1)
  - July-September 1955 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1960 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Articles (printed) (Box 1)
  - "Ghosts in Fiction" (Box 1)
  - "The Creative Process in Swinburne" (Box 1)
  - Re. Lord Byron (Box 1)
  - Re. Charles Dickens (Box 1)
  - Re. George Eliot (Box 1)
  - Re. Elizabeth Barrett Browning (Box 1)
  - Re. John Keats (Box 1)
  - Re. English Grammar (the sentence) (Box 1)
  - Re. George Meredith (Box 1)
  - Re. James Hogg (Box 1)
  - Re. Thomas Carlyle (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, fragmentary, and unidentified, 13 folders (Box 1)
- Other materials
  - Speech 1940 ? Modern Language Association (Box 1)
  - Examination questions, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - English 39 notes (Box 1)
  - R.W. Cowden student examinations (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)